A Finding Aid to the Maurice Becker Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.beckmaur
Archives of American Art
Maurice Becker papers
circa 1910-1970
AAA.beckmaur
Archives of American Art
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter and political cartoonist Maurice Becker measure 2.3 linear feet and date from circa 1910 to 1970. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence; writings; printed material, including radical labor and political periodicals; artwork; and photographs of Becker, his family and friends, and his artwork.
Becker, Maurice, 1889-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Maurice Becker donated his papers in several increments between 1962-1966.
Separated Materials note
There are scattered Maurice Becker papers found within the Art Young papers at the Tamiment Library in New York. These were loaned to the Archives in 1971 for microfilming on reel 96. These papers are not described in the container inventory of this finding aid but include approximately 20 postcards, catalogs, sketches, photographs, and other printed materials.
Duplicate magazines, catalogs, and clippings were transferred to the National Portrait Gallery Library in 1977.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection were microfilmed on 35 mm microfilm reels 128 and 4909. While the microfilm is available at the Archives of American Art offices and affliates, and through interlibrary loan, researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid, and may also be incomplete.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter and political cartoonist Maurice Becker (1889-1975) lived and worked in New York City, New York and Tioga County, Pennsylvania, and was a frequent contributor to contemporary periodicals of the 1910s.
Becker was born in Nizhni-Novgorod (now Gorky), Russia to Isor and Rose Becker. In 1892, his family immigrated to the United States and settled in the Jewish community of Manhattan's Lower East Side. After graduating from high school, Becker took night classes in bookkeeping and art, studied with Robert Henri and Hugo Boss, and worked days as a sign painter and garment factory worker. He began illustrating for the New York Tribune and Scripps newspapers from 1914 to 1915, and contributed artwork to numerous contemporary periodicals in the 1910s, including Harper’s Weekly, Saturday Review, and Metropolitan. Becker was also a frequent contributor to more radical political journals, including The Masses, Liberator, and One Big Union Monthly.
In 1918, he married Dorothy Baldwin, who was a registered Socialist. After stating his conscientious objection to World War I, Becker traveled to Mexico to avoid the draft and was arrested upon his return in 1919. After his trial and sentencing, he served 4 months of hard labor before President Wilson’s commutation of all objectors to the war. From 1921 to 1923, Becker lived in Mexico working as an illustrator for El Pulsa de México, and began to devote himself to painting full time.
After his return to New York City, Becker held a series of one-man shows at the Whitney Studio Club (1924-1928), J.B. Neumann Gallery (1924-1931), and Delphic Studios (1930). Becker was a member of the Society of Independent Artists and the Artists’ League of America and remained a pacifist for the rest of his life. He died in 1975.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and political cartoonist Maurice Becker measure 2.3 linear feet and date from circa 1910 to 1970. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence; writings; printed material, including radical labor and political periodicals; artwork; and photographs of Becker, his family and friends, and his artwork.
Biographical materials consist of a curriculum vitae and a list of artworks.
Correspondence is primarily with Becker’s family, friends, and business associates. There are letters from his wife, Dorothy Baldwin Becker, a letter from friend and artist Elizabeth Lancaster, and a letter from Artists for Victory. There is also a letter from Becker to his friend J. B. Neumann containing a draft of Becker's will authorizing Neumann to sell and distribute his paintings upon his death or incapacitation; a letter of invitation to artists and writers interested in reviving a new Masses style journal; and letters from magazine editors regarding freelance commissions.
Printed material includes bulletins, clippings and labor newspapers, exhibition announcements and catalogs, periodicals, press releases, and miscellaneous printed material. Periodicals include whole issues of Liberator, The Masses, New Masses, and One Big Union Monthly, where Becker’s political cartoons were frequently featured.
Artwork includes paintings, over 800 graphite and pen and ink sketches, watercolors, and prints depicting Becker’s figure drawings, caricatures, portrait drawings of men and women, and sketches of animals and landscapes. Many of these sketches were the basis for panels that later appeared in the New York Tribune, The Masses, and Liberator.
Photographs are of Maurice Becker with family and friends, and five photographs of his artwork.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical materials, 1925-1964 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1919-1964 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1920-1960 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed material, circa 1910-1970 (1 linear foot; Box 1, 4, OV 5)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1910-1965 (1.2 linear feet; Box 1-3, OV 6-8)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1910-1966 (3 folders; Box 3)
Artists for Victory, Inc; Becker, Dorothy Baldwin; Lancaster, Elizabeth G., (Elizabeth Grieg), 1889-; Neumann, J. B. (Jsrael Ber); Caricatures and cartoons--New York (State)--New York; Cartooning -- United States; Cartoonists -- New York (State) -- New York; Liberator (New York, N.Y.: 1918); Masses (New York, N.Y.); New masses; Painters -- New York (State)-- New York; Painting, American -- New York (State) -- New York; Paintings; Photographs; Politics in art; Prints; Sketches; Watercolors
- Biographical Materials, 1925-1964; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials consist of a curriculum vitae and a list of artworks dating from 1927 to 1959.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1925-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of Artworks, circa 1925-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1919-1964; Series 2; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Becker’s family, friends, and business associates. The series includes correspondence from his wife, Dorothy Baldwin Becker, letters from magazine editors regarding freelance commissions, and correspondence from artist friend Elizabeth Lancaster. There are also draft copies of Becker's will dating from 1956 and a letter of invitation to artists and writers interested in reviving a new Masses style journal dating from 1925.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 1919-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Becker, Dorothy Baldwin, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Becker, Maurice, 1919-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Illegible and Unknown, circa 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings, circa 1920-1960; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1
  Writings consist of notes by Becker and an excerpt from an essay describing Becker’s exhibition at the Artists’ League of America by an unknown author.
  - Essay, "Formalism Uber Alles," Unknown Author, circa 1920-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes, circa 1920-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, circa 1910-1970; Series 4; 1 Linear feet Box 1, 4, OV 5
  Printed material includes bulletins, clippings and labor newspapers, exhibition announcements and catalogs, periodicals, press releases, and miscellaneous printed material. Periodicals include whole issues of Liberator, The Masses, New Masses, and One Big Union Monthly, where Becker’s political cartoons were frequently featured. Other radical magazines and newspapers include Blast, Maccabaean, Revolt, and Worker’s Monthly are also included in the series.
  - Booklet, City Where Crime is Play, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bulletins, 1937, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Oversized material housed in OV 5.
  - Clippings, 1912-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, circa 1920-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Labor Newspapers, 1916-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, F1.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1929-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, 1927-1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Periodicals (Box 1)
    - Americana, circa 1935-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Art News, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Arts, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Blast, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Coming Nation, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, F2.
    - Good Morning, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Harper's Weekly, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - L'Assiette au Beurre, circa 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - La Revue Moderne, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Les Annales, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Liberator, 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
    - Liberator, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 34-37)
    - Maccabaean, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Mainstream, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Masses, 1954; 1913-1917; 1911 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, F3-6.
    - New Masses, 1944; 1927 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
    - New York Call, 1913-1914, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, F7.
    - One Big Union Monthly, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Pathfinder, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Studio News, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Survey, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Worker's Monthly, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Miscellaneous Periodicals, 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Oversized material housed in Box 4, F8.
  - Press Release, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1920-1970 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, Artwork, circa 1920-1970 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Oversized Clippings, circa 1910-1965 (Box OV 5)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F11.
  - Oversized Labor Newspaper, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F16.
  - Oversized Periodical, Coming Nation, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F24.
  - Oversized Periodical, Masses, 1913-1916 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F40.
  - Oversized Periodical, New York Call, 1913-1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F43.
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Periodicals, 1954-1964 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F49.
- Artwork, circa 1910-1965; Series 5; 1.2 Linear feet Box 1-3, OV 6-8
  Artwork includes paintings, over 800 graphite and pen and ink sketches, watercolors, and prints depicting Becker’s figure drawings, caricatures, portrait drawings of men and women, and sketches of animals and landscapes. Many of these sketches were the basis for panels that later appeared in the New York Tribune, The Masses, and Liberator. Labor leaders, politicians, and artists identified in these sketches include Mother Jones, Samuel Gompers, Herbert Hoover, William Glackens, and Max Eastman.
  - Paintings, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Oversized material housed in OV 7.
  - Pastel, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Pen and Ink, Caricatures, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Oversized material housed in OV 6 and OV 7.
  - Pen and Ink, Figures, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 7.
  - Pen and Ink, Groups, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 6.
  - Pen and Ink, Men, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Pen and Ink, Women, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Oversized material housed in OV 6.
  - Pen and Ink, Animals and Landscapes, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Prints, circa 1920-1965 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Sketchbook, Pen and Ink, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Sketches, Artists, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Sketches, Caricatures, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Sketches, Family, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Sketches, Labor Organizers, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Sketches, Mexico, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Sketches, Politicians, circa 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Sketches, Trial Coverage, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Sketches, Other Identified Individuals, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sketches, Groups, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 6 and OV 8.
  - Sketches, Men, Figures, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    Oversized material housed in OV 8.
  - Sketches, Men, Figures and Portraits, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sketches, Men, Portraits, circa 1910-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8-12)
  - Sketches, Men and Women, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Sketches, Women, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sketches, Women, Figures, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sketches, Animals, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sketches, Landscapes, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Watercolors, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Other Artists, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Painting and Pen and Inks, circa 1910-1965 (Box OV 7)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F53, F55-56.
  - Oversized Pen and Inks and Sketches, circa 1910-1965 (Box OV 6)
    Oversized material from Box 1, F55, F57, F60-61; Box 2, F3, F8; and Box 3, F1.
  - Oversized Sketches, circa 1910-1965 (Box OV 8)
    Oversized material from Box 2, F3, F5.
- Photographs, circa 1910-1966; Series 6; 3 Folders Box 3
  Photographs are of Maurice Becker with family and friends, and five photographs of his artwork.
  Materials are arranged by subject type.
  - Photographs of Maurice Becker, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Dorothy Baldwin Becker, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1910-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)